Fabio Pagani

AFFILIATION Vulnerability Research Lead, Binarly

CONTACT INFORMATION pagani@ucsb.edu
 https://pagabuc.me

♥ @pagabuc

▼ FabioPagani

Bio

I am a Vulnerability Research Lead at Binarly, where I work at the intersection of static and dynamic analysis techniques to help secure the UEFI ecosystem.

Previously, I was a postdoctoral researcher working with Giovanni Vigna and Christopher Kruegel in the SecLab at UC Santa Barbara. My current research interests focus on different aspects of systems security: automated vulnerability discovery, human-assisted cyber reasoning systems, and malware analysis are all topics that spark my curiosity.

I earned a Ph.D at EURECOM, where I was advised by Davide Balzarotti. Among other things, we investigated how non-atomic acquisitions impact the consistency of memory dumps, how to discover and to assess the quality of memory forensics heuristics, and how to automatically generate profiles for memory forensics.

When I am away from keyboard, I enjoy hiking, rock climbing, surfing, and playing chess.

EXPERIENCE

Vulnerability Research Lead

Jun 2024-Present

Binarly

Principal Research Scientist

Mar 2023-Jun 2024

Binarly

Postdoctoral Researcher

Jan 2020-Mar 2023

University of California, Santa Barbara, US

Doctor in Philosophy (PhD)

Jan 2016-Sept 2019

Eurecom, France

Thesis: Advances in Memory Forensics

EDUCATION

MSc in Computer Science

Feb 2013-Oct 2015

Universitá degli Studi di Milano, Italy

Thesis: Defeating Return Oriented Programming Attacks Using Program Analysis Techniques Graduated with a final grade of 110/110 cum laude

Internship Feb 2015-May 2015

Eurecom, France

Erasmus Jan 2014-Jun 2014

Uppsala University, Sweden

BSc in Computer Science

Sep 2009-Feb 2013

Universitá degli Studi di Milano, Italy

Thesis: When Hardware Meets Software: A Bulletproof Solution to Forensic Memory Acquisition Graduated with a final grade of 107/110

TALKS

[5] **Fabio Pagani**, Alex Matrosov, Yegor Vasilenko, Sam Thomas, Anton Ivanov. PKfail: Supply-Chain Failures in Secure Boot Key Management. LABScon 2024

- [4] **Fabio Pagani**, Alex Matrosov, Alex Ermolov, Yegor Vasilenko, Sam Thomas, Anton Ivanov. LogoFAIL: Security Implications of Image Parsing During System Boot. BlackHat EU 2023
- [3] Victor Duta, Fabian Freyer, **Fabio Pagani**, Marius Muench, Cristiano Giuffrida. Unwinding the Stack for Fun and Profit. Black Hat EU 2022
- [2] Nicola Ruaro, **Fabio Pagani**, Stefano Ortolani, Giovanni Vigna. Symbexcel: Bringing the Power of Symbolic Execution to the Fight Against Malicious Excel 4 Macros. Black Hat USA 2021
- [1] Fabio Pagani. Memory Smearing: Myth Or Reality?. SANS DFIR Europe Summit 2019

PUBLICATIONS

- [14] Victor Duta, Fabian Freyer, **Fabio Pagani**, Marius Muench, Cristiano Giuffrida. Let Me Unwind That For You: Exceptions to Backward-Edge Protection. In Proceedings of the Network and Distributed Systems Security Symposium (NDSS 2023)
- [13] Erik Trickel, **Fabio Pagani**, Chang Zhu, Lukas Dresel, Giovanni Vigna, Christopher Kruegel, Ruoyu Wang, Tiffany Bao, Yan Shoshitaishvili, Adam Doupe. Toss a Fault to Your Witcher: Applying Grey-box Coverage-Guided Mutational Fuzzing to Detect SQL and Command Injection Vulnerabilities. In Proceedings of the 43rd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P 2023)
- [12] Kevin Burk, **Fabio Pagani**, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna. Decomperson: How Humans Decompile and What We Can Learn From It. In Proceedings of the 31st USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 22)
- [11] Nicola Ruaro, **Fabio Pagani**, Stefano Ortolani, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna. Symbexcel: Automated Analysis and Understanding of Malicious Excel 4.0 Macros. In Proceedings of the 43rd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P 2022)
- [10] Fabio Gritti, **Fabio Pagani**, Ilya Grishchenko, Lukas Dresel, Nilo Redini, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna. HEAPSTER: Analyzing the Security of Dynamic Allocators for Monolithic Firmware Images. In Proceedings of the 43rd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P 2022)
- [9] **Fabio Pagani**, Davide Balzarotti. AutoProfile: Towards Automated Profile Generation For Memory Analysis. ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) 25, no. 1 (2022)
- [8] Robert McLaughlin, **Fabio Pagani**, Noah Spahn, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna. Regulator: Dynamic Analysis To Detect ReDoS. In Proceedings of the 31st USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 22)
- [7] Fabio Gritti, Lorenzo Fontana, Eric Gustafson, **Fabio Pagani**, Andrea Continella, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna. SYMBION: Interleaving Symbolic With Concrete Execution. In Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Communications and Network Security (CNS) 2020
- [6] **Fabio Pagani**, Davide Balzarotti. Back to the Whiteboard: a Principled Approach for the Assessment and Design of Memory Forensic Techniques. In Proceedings of the 28th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security 19) 2019
- [5] **Fabio Pagani**, Oleksii Fedorov, Davide Balzarotti. Introducing the Temporal Dimension to Memory Forensics. ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) 22, no. 2 (2019)
- [4] **Fabio Pagani**, Matteo Dell'Amico, Davide Balzarotti. Beyond Precision and Recall: Understanding Uses (and Misuses) of Similarity Hashes in Binary Analysis. In Proceedings of the Eighth ACM Conference on Data and Application Security and Privacy (CODASPY) 2018
- [3] Marius Muench, **Fabio Pagani**, Yan Shoshitaishvili, Christopher Kruegel, Giovanni Vigna, Davide Balzarotti. Taming Transactions: Towards Hardware-Assisted Control Flow Integrity Using Transactional Memory. In International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusions, and Defenses (RAID) 2016

- [2] **Fabio Pagani**, Matteo De Astis, Mariano Graziano, Andrea Lanzi, Davide Balzarotti. Measuring the Role of Greylisting and Nolisting in Fighting Spam. In Proceedings of the 46th Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN) 2016
- [1] Alessandro Reina, Aristide Fattori, **Fabio Pagani**, Lorenzo Cavallaro, Danilo Bruschi. When Hardware Meets Software: a Bulletproof Solution to Forensic Memory Acquisition. In Proceedings of the 28th Annual Computer Security Applications Conference (ACSAC) 2012

AWARDS

- [3] Distinguished Reviewer Award DIMVA 2021
- [2] Volatility Plugin Contest 2019, 5th place
- [1] Black Hat Europe 2016 Student Scholarship

SERVICE

IEEE Workshop on Offensive Technologies (WOOT) 2024

USENIX Security 2024

IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2023

Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA) 2023

IEEE Workshop on Offensive Technologies (WOOT) 2023

Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA) 2022

Digital Forensics Research Workshop (DFRWS) USA 2022

IEEE Workshop on Offensive Technologies (WOOT) 2022

Workshop on Binary Analysis Research (BAR) 2022

Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA) 2021

Computers & Security (COSE)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lecture on Memory Forensics (Cybercrime and Computer Forensics) Eurecom, France

Apr. 2019

Eurecom, France

Lecture on Python Optimization and Integration (Software Development)

Eurecom, France

Dec. 2018

Lecture on Memory Forensics (Cybercrime and Computer Forensics)

May 2018

Eurecom, France

Lecture on Python Optimization and Integration (Software Development)

Dec. 2017

Eurecom, France

Lecture on Python Optimization and Integration (Software Development)

Eurecom, France

Dec. 2016

Computer Programming - Teaching Assistant

Universitá degli Studi di Milano, Italy

Sept. 2014 - Feb. 2015

HACKING COMPETITIONS

I am part of Shellphish, and I helped with the organization of iCTF 2021 and Decompetition V1 and V2.

I am also a core member of the NOPS team. As a team, we qualified twice for the CSAW Europe Finals (with a 2nd place in 2017) and we **won** hxp CTF 2018.